<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Directions for seeker &amp; expectants, or, A guide for weak Christians in these distracted times wherein the language of Sions-builders is confounded : as it was delivered in a sermon at Wickham-Market ... published at the earnest entreatie of many, for a more publique good / by Zeph. Smith, Minister of Wickham-Market in Suffolke.</title>
            <author>Smyth, Zeph. (Zephaniah), fl. 1646-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4362</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37570</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16975852</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16975852</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105582</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60679)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105582)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1159:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Directions for seeker &amp; expectants, or, A guide for weak Christians in these distracted times wherein the language of Sions-builders is confounded : as it was delivered in a sermon at Wickham-Market ... published at the earnest entreatie of many, for a more publique good / by Zeph. Smith, Minister of Wickham-Market in Suffolke.</title>
                  <author>Smyth, Zeph. (Zephaniah), fl. 1646-1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Matthew Simmons for John Sweeting ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"May the 16th 1646. Imprimatur, John Downame."</note>
                  <note>Running title: Directions for seekers and weake Christians.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXIX, 102 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105582:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105582:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DIRECTIONS FOR Seekers &amp; Expectants, <hi>OR</hi> A Guide for weake Chriſtians in theſe diſtracted times.</p>
            <p>Wherein the language of <hi>Sions</hi>-buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders is confounded.</p>
            <p>As it was delivered in a Sermon at <hi>Wickham-Market.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preached on purpoſe to ſettle poore weake Chriſtians, who are in great danger of miſcarrying, by reaſon of ſeducers, in theſe erroneous times.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed at the earneſt intreatie of many, for a more publique good.</p>
            <p>By ZEPH: SMITH, Miniſter of <hi>Wickham-Market</hi> in <hi>Suffolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 25.9.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Who ſo among you feares the Lord, him will he teach: the humble will he teach his way.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1646.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> John Downame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Matthew Simmons</hi> for <hi>John Sweeting,</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Popes</hi>-head-Alley. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105582:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> weak Chriſtians, called <hi>Expectants</hi> and <hi>See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> who take notice of ſo many ſeverall opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they ſuppoſe no body is in the right way, and therefore will waite untill God diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſome new way to them, which was never yet heard of. To whom I have given Directions in my Sermon what to doe, that they might know the way of God, and no longer halt between two opinions. Theſe cauſes moved me to conſent to the publiſhing of it; and <hi>Chriſtian Reader,</hi> when thou readeſt, whether thou findeſt abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or weakneſſe, let God have the glory, who giveth to every one as it pleaſeth him; and if God may have the glory, and any poore Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an be by the reading of it the better eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the truth, and for the time to come try be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he truſt, the Author ſhall have his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, who is willing, God inabling him, to ſpend and be ſpent for the ſame purpoſe; which that it may be, the Author will pray, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ZEPH: SMITH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105582:2"/>
            <head>DIRECTIONS FOR SEEKERS AND WEAKE CHRISTIANS in theſe diſtracted Times.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 119.102.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—For thou haſt taught mee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Pſalme</hi> is a <hi>Pſalme</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> and as the whole Booke of <hi>Pſalmes</hi> is full of heavenly matter, and ſoule-raviſhing expreſſions; ſo this <hi>Pſalme</hi> is in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall manner. The man of God was much taken up with GOD, and his Word, his Statutes, and Judgements, in ſo much, that he knew not how to meditate enough, and how to ſpeake enough of it; the Prophet found ſuch a ſweetneſſe in Gods Word, that notwithſtanding he knew much of it, yet ſtill he deſires to know more, and therefore it is his expreſſion very often in the <hi>Pſalmes, Lord, teach;</hi> and, <hi>Oh, teach me thy ſtatutes.</hi> The Prophet <hi>David</hi> was not of the minde that proud generation is of, that ſay, they know as much as all the Preachers in the Countrey can tell them, nay, as much as God himſelfe can teach them, they thinke, otherwiſe what meanes that damnable Doctrine that is broached in theſe dayes, when
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105582:3"/>we have received the Spirit, the Letter ſhould ceaſe; contrary to <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.25. <hi>That which yee have already, hold faſt untill I come.</hi> But the Prophet, though he knew much, yet he deſires to know more; neither was the Prophet like that ſort of hearers, which may be compared unto the ſtony ground, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. who receive the Word into their heads, but not into their hearts, that they might bring forth fruit in their lives, to the honour of God; for in the 11. verſe of this <hi>Pſalme, Thy Word,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>have I hid in my heart, that I might not ſinne againſt thee.</hi> The Prophet did not only labour after the knowledge of the Word, but he put it into practice. Neither can it be ſaid of the Prophet, as it may of too too many profeſſors now adayes, they are young Saints and old Devils, they begin in the Spirit, and end in the fleſh; the uncleane ſpirit is caſt out for a time, but it returns againe: for the Prophet did perſevere in the practicing of thoſe truths which God did teach him, and which he did profeſſe; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the Text; <hi>I have not declined from thy Judgements, for thou haſt taught me.</hi> In which conſider two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, The Perſon teaching, <hi>God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, The Perſon taught, <hi>David.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>From the perſon teaching, we are not onely to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der who it was, but what it was which he taught, <hi>His Judgements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the perſon taught, wee are to conſider; firſt, his tractablenes to learne that which God did teach him; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, his conſtancy in the practice of thoſe truths which God did teach him; thirdly, the ground why he practiced thoſe truths, becauſe God taught him. Give me leave, briefly, to open the words, and then to come to ſome point of Doctrine. And firſt, what he meaneth when he ſaith; <hi>I have not declined;</hi> that is, I have not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105582:3"/>or gone backe from the way of thy Judgements; I have not left the wayes of God, to walke in the wayes of wickedneſſe. Secondly, What is meant by <hi>Judgements? Anſw.</hi> Gods Lawes; by <hi>Judgements</hi> is meant his Lawes. Gods Lawes have ſeverall names in Scripture; ſometime they are called <hi>his wayes;</hi> as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.1. Sometimes <hi>his teſtimonies,</hi> Pſal. 119.2. <hi>His precepts,</hi> verſ. 4. <hi>His ſtatutes,</hi> verſ. 5. <hi>His Commandements,</hi> verſ. 6. <hi>His Judgements,</hi> verſ. 7. and the Text; ſo in verſ. 13. and verſ. 20. Sometimes <hi>bis Word,</hi> verſ. 9. So that by <hi>Judgements,</hi> is meant, Gods Statutes, Lawes, and Commandements; as will appeare if we conſider the following verſes unto the 107. Then thirdly, What doth the Prophet meane, when he ſaith, <hi>For thou haſt taught me?</hi> He doth not ſay, the Miniſters my teachers taught me, and therefore I profited by them, but becauſe God taught him, that is, God made the outward Miniſtery of the Word effectuall by the inward operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Spirit; not that the Prophet did neglect attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the outward Miniſtery of the Word, and reſted altogether upon the teaching of the Spirit, without the Word; for the Prophet tooke delight in attending up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Word preached; it was the onely thing he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. that he <hi>panted after,</hi> Pſal. 42.1. that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyced in the injoyment of, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. Neither did he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit by the outward Miniſtery of the Word onely; for <hi>Paul <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay plant, and Apollo water, but God giveth the increaſe;</hi> but God made the outward Miniſtry of the Word effectuall by the inward operation of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>The Text is the ground and reaſon why the Prophet <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id profit in Gods Lawes, why he kept them, and was conſtant in the practice of them, becauſe God taught <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im; from whence may ariſe this poynt of Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That God is the beſt teacher and inſtructer of his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:105582:4"/>
            <p> And for the method, I, God aſſiſting, will ſhew you that it is ſo, and how it appeares to be ſo; ſecondly, the means by which God doth teach the ſoule; thirdly, the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Gods teaching above mans teaching; fourthly, the manner; fiftly, the grounds; ſixtly, application.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That it is ſo appeares in the Text, wherein is ſet out the excellency of Gods teaching above mans: ſo in <hi>Job</hi> 36.22. <hi>Behold, God exalteth by his power; for none teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth like him:</hi> He is more excellent in his teaching then all others; ſo that you ſee that it is ſo; next, I come to ſhew you that it muſt needs be ſo, as appeares three wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He is the Author of all other faithfull Preachers of the Word, it is God that fits all other faithfull Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the Word for the worke of the Miniſtry; it is not all the arts and ſciences in the world, that can make a man fit for the work of the Miniſtry, if God fit him not, it is God who maketh able Miniſters of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Who hath made us able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit.</hi> Arts and Sciences are helpes and handmaids to Divinitie, but it is God that makes able Miniſters of the New Teſtament; <hi>And he gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers:</hi> He gave, it is, he gave and he fitted for the worke of the Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God is the Author of all the doctrinal truths which all the faithfull Preachers in the world deliver un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to people, he is the Author of thoſe truths; he ſends all the faithfull Miniſters of the Word in his Name to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Meſſage unto his people; <hi>Sonne of man, give them warning from mee,</hi> Ezek. 3.17. And he ſends the Prophets often with this Meſſage; <hi>Goe tell them, Thus ſaith the Lord;</hi> and, <hi>This is the word of the Lord:</hi> and the Prophets when they delivered his Meſſage unto the people; <hi>Heare yee</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105582:4"/>ſay they, <hi>what the Lord ſaith:</hi> they did not deliver the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of their owne braine, but the Word of the Lord; and the Apoſtles were to teach and obſerve what Chriſt had commanded, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. laſt verſe: and all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters of the Goſpel now they deliver Gods Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage unto the people, and are to deliver nothing but that which they can ſay, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> Iſai. 8.20. So that God is the Author of all the truths which the faithfull Miniſters of the Word deliver unto the people.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is the Lord which gives ſucceſſe to the faithfull preaching of the Word, the Miniſter can but with the ſervant of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> lay the ſtaffe upon the face of the childe, they can but propound the minde and will of God unto people, preach the Word, and baptize with water, but they cannot make the Word effectuall, and the Sacraments effectuall, that is the work of God; <hi>Paul may plant, and Apollo water, but it is God that gives a bleſsing;</hi> and, <hi>It is not in him which willeth, and him which runneth, but in God that gives a bleſsing;</hi> therefore the Goſpel is ſaid to <hi>be the power of God through faith to ſalvation; and the weapons of the word are mightie through God, to the pulling downe of ſtrong holds.</hi> Now lay all theſe together, God is the Author of the Miniſter, of the doctrine, and of the ſucceſſe, and it will appeare a plaine truth, that <hi>God is the beſt teacher of his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It appeares God is the beſt teacher of his people, by the directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that the Lord gives in his Word unto teachers and hearers, how they ſhould teach and heare aright; he gives directions unto Miniſters to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to <hi>ſhew themſelves approved of God, workmen that need not to be aſhamed, dividing the word of truth aright,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.15. <hi>To preach the word in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, to reprove, rebuke, and exhort, with all long-ſuffering and doctrine,</hi> 2
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105582:5"/>Tim. 4.23. <hi>And convince them ſharply, that they may be ſound in the faith,</hi> Tit. 1.3. So he directs people how they ſhould heare aright, he bids them <hi>try the Spirits, whether they be of God,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.1. As the men of <hi>Berea, who ſearched the Scriptures,</hi> Acts 17.11. Hearers ſhould not receive any kind of doctrine for truth, <hi>but try the ſpirits,</hi> and <hi>receive with meekneſſe the ingrafted word,</hi> James 1.21. Now he that is able to teach both teacher and hearers how they ſhould teach and heare aright, muſt needs be the beſt teacher himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It appeares God is the ſoules beſt inſtructor by the great deſire of the Saints to be taught of God, though they injoy mans teaching, yet this contenteth them not, except God teach them. How often is it the expreſſion of the Prophet <hi>David, Lord teach me,</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.11. <hi>Teach me thy way, O Lord?</hi> ſo often in this 119. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> the Prophet begs of God to teach him, in the 12. verſe, in verſ. 26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 33. <hi>&amp;</hi> 66. <hi>&amp;</hi> 68. <hi>&amp;</hi> 108.124. In all theſe verſes the Prophet prayeth to God to teach him. And as this was <hi>Davids</hi> prayer, ſo it is the prayer and deſire of all ſuch gracious ſpirits as <hi>David</hi> was. All thoſe that are men and women according to Gods owne heart, as <hi>David</hi> was, will with <hi>David</hi> pray, <hi>Lord teach mee.</hi> Now the great deſire of the Saints to be taught of God, ſhews <hi>God is the ſoules beſt inſtructor, the beſt teacher of his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place we come to the means, by which God doth teach the ſoule; and this is two-fold, outwardly by the Miniſtry of the Word, and inwardly by his Spirit; by the Word and the Spirit, this is the ordinary way; firſt, by his Word, he teaches his people by the preaching of the Word, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21. The Lord is pleaſed <hi>by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe of preaching to ſave them that believe;</hi> that is, by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105582:5"/>that means which the world counts fooliſhneſſe, not that it is fooliſhneſſe in it ſelfe, but it is ſo to the wicked, that is, the wicked accounteth it fooliſhneſſe. In verſ. 18. the <hi>preaching of the Croſſe is to them which periſh fooliſhneſſe,</hi> but it is not ſo to the godly, <hi>to us which are ſaved it is the power of God:</hi> and therefore <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Faith comes by hearing;</hi> this is the ordinary means the Lord hath appointed for the working faith in the hearts of his people; this is the outward meanes. But then ſecondly, there is the inward teaching of the ſoule, and that is by the Spirit, the Lord teaches his people by his Spirit, that is, the Lord makes the outward Miniſtry of the Word effectuall by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward operation of the Spirit, when he ſhews a divine power and authoritie in the preaching of the Word, when he makes it become mightie and powerfull in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to the pulling downe of ſtrong holds; as in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. That is, to the pulling downe of the ſtrong holds in the heart, that exalt themſelves againſt the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and prepare the heart for Chriſt; this is the worke of the Spirit, and without this the letter doth not profit the people, but God therefore teaches his people by his Spirit, he hath revealed them to us by his Spirit; for the <hi>Spirit ſearches the deepe things of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.10. It is the Spirit that cauſes the Word to take impreſſion upon the hearts of people; and therefore when the Lord maketh the Miniſtry of the Word ſuccesfull, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are made able Miniſters of the Spirit, as in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p>In the third place, I am to ſhew you the excellency of Gods teaching above mans; and that appeares foure wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Earthly teachers can but propound the mind and will of God unto the people, they cannot make the ſoule
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105582:6"/>to ſtoop to thoſe truths, and practice thoſe truths which they teach; but herein appeares the Excellency of Gods teaching above mans, he can make the ſoule to yeeld obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto the truth delivered, he can bring the ſoule under the power of thoſe truths. See the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> expreſſion to this purpoſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.2. <hi>Thine arrowes ſticke faſt in me, and thy hand preſſeth me ſore:</hi> When God comes to teach a ſoule, he will ſhoot the arrowes ſo faſt, that it ſhall take impreſſion, the ſoule ſhall come under the power of truths, ſo that the ſoule ſhall ſay, Lord I would faine have ſhaken off thine arrowes, but am not able, for they ſticke faſt in mee. And thus God did teach thoſe in the <hi>Acts, Act.</hi> 2.39. <hi>When they heard this, they were pricked in their hearts;</hi> it was not the bare words of the Apoſtle, when he told them, <hi>You are the parties that have crucified the Lord of glory,</hi> that did pricke their hearts, but the Lord ſet it home to their conſciences, and brought them under the power of that truth they heard, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the voyce of man, but the voyce of God in that word of truth, and then they were pricked in their hearts. And thus God did teach <hi>Lydia,</hi> he opened her heart, and then ſhee attended to that which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14. It was not <hi>Paul</hi> opened her heart, but God opened <hi>Lydia's</hi> heart. A man may heare a thouſand Sermons, and yet get no good, if he heare onely the voyce of a man, but if the day of Gods power come upon the ſoule, that he heare the voyce of God in the Ordinances, then he ſhall profit; for Gods voyce in his Word is a commanding voyce, <hi>Job</hi> 36.10. <hi>He commanded them to returne from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</hi> Gods teaching the ſoule is with a command, with ſuch Authoritie, as the ſoule cannot reſiſt it. And herein appears the excellency of Gods teaching the ſoule above mans.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105582:6"/>
            <p> Secondly, Gods teaching the ſoule is more excellent then mans, if wee conſider the time of his teaching the ſoule. The Miniſter can teach them but ſome times, <hi>in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon,</hi> but God can teach the ſoule at all times, in the abſence of teachers; for either our teachers may be taken from us, or wee from them, but God can then teach the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we conſider the place where he doth teach, the Miniſter doth preach in the publique aſſembly, but God can teach in all places, and teach at once in all places, which no other teacher can doe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If wee conſider the perſons which he doth teach, the Miniſter doth preach but to ſome of Gods people, but God doth teach all his people himſelfe, they are all taught of him. And as God doth teach all his people, ſo he can teach them all at once; the Miniſter can teach but ſome at once, but God can teach all the Congregations that doe aſſemble together at once, he is not ſo much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in one Congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but he can be as much in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at one and the ſame time to teach his people. So that conſider the time, the place, and the perſons, and in all theſe it will appeare Gods teaching is more excellent then mans.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Gods teaching the ſoule is more excellent then mans; it appeares if we conſider the infallibilitie of Gods teaching and inſtructing his people, he is an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible teacher, he doth teach the ſoule infallible truths. Earthly teachers are not infallible teachers, though they be faithfull and endeavour to deliver the truth, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the truth unto people, yet they are but men, and may erre; but God cannot erre in teaching of his people, for he doth teach his people according to his Word, which is infallible: <hi>Heaven and earth ſhall periſh, but not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105582:7"/>one jot or tittle ſhall fall.</hi> But here may ariſe an objection, God doth teach his people by the outward Miniſtry of the Word, but the Miniſter is not infallible, <hi>ergo,</hi> God is not an infallible teacher of his people. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Word of God is an infallible Word, and this is that God doth teach his people by: then ſecondly, it is when the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter hits upon the true interpretation of Scripture, when he doth give the true ſenſe and meaning of the Holy Ghoſt from a Text that the Spirit of God doth accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany it, and make it profitable unto the people; for wee muſt note the Spirit of God doth not goe along with a falſe interpretation of Scripture, but with the true ſenſe; for Gods Spirit doth accompany the truth man delivers, and not the error; ſo that ſtill it will hold a truth, <hi>Man may erre, but God is the infallible teacher and inſtructor of his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, The excellency of Gods teaching above mans, appeares in the ſutableneſſe of the matter of the perſons condition which he doth teach: Miniſters may endeavour to prepare matter ſutable to the conditions of the people they teach, but they may be miſtaken; but the Lord knows the hearts of all his people, and he knows what truths are moſt ſutable to their conditions, and he doth teach them ſutable to their conditions. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a ſpirit be wounded, which is a burthen who can beare? The Lord will come with ſutable matter to ſuch a ſoule, he tels it, I have ſent Jeſus Chriſt for to bind up the broken-hearted ſinner, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 61.1. And the Sonne of man is come to ſeeke and ſave loſt ſinners, ſuch as ſee themſelves loſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.11. Nay, he bids them come; <hi>Come all yee that are weary and heavy laden, and I will eaſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you;</hi> that is, you that feele ſinne a burthen, and ſtrive to get from under this burthen, come to me and I will eaſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105582:7"/>you. Suppoſe the ſoule be ſicke, he propounds Chriſt as a Phyſitian to the ſick-ſoule; if the ſoule be hungry and thirſty after righteouſneſs, he propounds Chriſt as bread of life, and water of life, and invites poore ſoules to come to him; <hi>Hoe, every one that thirſteth, come yee to the waters, come buy without ſilver and without money,</hi> Iſai. 54.1. <hi>And if any man thirſt, let him come unto mee and drinke,</hi> Joh. 7.37. Suppoſe a ſoule be in depths of deſertion, walke in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſee no light, but when he lookes up to heaven, and thinkes upon God, he is troubled, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.3. It thinks that God hath forſaken it, and will never returne againe in mercy, the Lord doth ſay to ſuch a ſoule, <hi>Let him truſt in the Name of the Lord,</hi> Iſai. 50.10. <hi>For a moment in my anger I hid my face, but with everlaſting mercy I had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion on thee, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Iſai. 54.8. Suppoſe a ſoule ſhould ſuffer the loſſe of all for Chriſts ſake; <hi>He that loſeth houſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands, ſhall receive an hundred-fold in this life, and in the world to come life everlaſting.</hi> Not that they ſhall receive for the loſſe of one wife a hundred, or of one houſe a hundred, but that comfort that will make up all a hundred-fold, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.29. Suppoſe a ſoule be to ſuffer for Chriſts ſake, <hi>I will</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>be with thee in the fire, and the water,</hi> as Iſai. 43.4. <hi>that it ſhall not hurt thee:</hi> ſo to the poore ſoule that doth ſay, Sinne will overcome <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and get the day when I have done what I can, and I <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall never be able to overcome ſuch and ſuch corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I ſhall never be able to overcome Satans temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Well, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Sinne ſhall not have dominion ever your mortall bodies,</hi> Rom. 6.14. <hi>And the God of peace <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all tread Satan under your feet ſhortly,</hi> Rom. 6.20. <hi>And one ſhall ever be able to plucke my ſheep out of my hands,</hi> Joh. <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.28. So the ſoule that is ignorant of Gods wayes, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105582:8"/>cryes out, Oh I know not whether I be in the right way or no, there are ſo many ſeverall opinions. <hi>I will teach thee</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>in the way that thou ſhalt goe,</hi> Pſal. 32.8. <hi>And thy eares ſhall heare a voyce behinde thee, ſaying, This is the way,</hi> Iſai. 30.21. And as in theſe, ſo in any condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that the Lord doth teach ſutable to the condition of the ſoule. And thus having ſhewed you the excellency of Gods teaching his people above mans; it followes next to ſhew you the manner of his teaching.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Lord doth teach the ſoule to know its mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery without Jeſus Chriſt, he opens the underſtanding, and inlightneth the minde, and cauſeth the ſoule to ſee its loſt condition. Secondly, He doth it with power, the day of his power came upon the ſoule, <hi>the people ſhall be willing in the day of thy power,</hi> Pſal. 110. The Lord doth not onely open the underſtanding, &amp; inlighten the mind, but cauſeth the ſoule to lye under the power of thoſe truths. Then thirdly, he doth uſe arguments of convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by which he doth convince the ſinner of his miſery, and of the neceſſitie of Jeſus Chriſt. When the ſoule ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, It is but the opinion of the Miniſter, and God is mercifull, and he that made us, will ſave us. The Lord makes anſwer, It is not the Miniſter, but the Scripture, that <hi>concludes all under ſinne,</hi> Gal. 3.22. And whereas thou ſayeſt, God is mercifull; <hi>He that heares the words of this curſe, and bleſſeth himſelfe in his heart, and ſaith, I ſhall have peace, though I walke according to the imagination of my heart, the Lord will not be mercifull to him; nay, his wrath and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie ſhall ſmoake againſt him,</hi> Deut. 29.19. <hi>And he that made you, will not ſave you, and he that formed you, will not have mercy on you,</hi> Iſai. 27.11. And the Lord doth not onely propound this unto the ſoule, but brings the ſoule under the power of theſe truths: the Lord beats the ſinner of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105582:8"/>all the props he leans upon beſides Jeſus Chriſt the Lord, makes all the arguments effectuall; if he ſpeak, it is done; if he ſay to the blind eyes, be opened, and to the deafe eares, be opened, they ſhall be opened; if he ſay to the dead ſoule, live, it ſhall live; in that day the eares of the deaſe ſhall be opened, and the eyes of the blind ſhall ſee out of obſcuritie and darkneſſe, and the dead ſhall heare the voyce of Jeſus Chriſt and live; and ſo it is with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Lord teacheth the ſoule, whether in the worke of preparation for Chriſt, or direction how to live after the ſoule hath received Chriſt, the Lord doth not onely propound the truth to them, but brings them under the power of it.</p>
            <p>Next we come to the Reaſons, why God is the beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructor of his people.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> God is the beſt inſtructor of his people, becauſe he is the ableſt teacher and inſtructor of his people, he is the ableſt for matter, manner, and meaſure; firſt, he is the ableſt for matter; that which God teacheth is infallible truth, now there is no man that is infallible for matter; for the doctrine of faithful Miniſters may have much fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in it, they are men and may erre, but God cannot erre, all that he teacheth the ſoul is truth, infallible truth, nothing but truth, truth without mixture, and there is <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o truth the ſoule deſires to have cleared up, but God is able to do it, and not onely a part of truth, but the whole truth. A poore ſoule may goe to this Miniſter, and that Miniſter, and ſay, Sir, I would faine be reſolved, whether <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch and ſuch a thing be truth, and they may direct them ſo farre as they can, but when they have done what they <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an, yet the partie may be in a great part unreſolved; why, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Miniſters know but in part, but God knows the whole <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uth, and is able to teach the ſoule the whole truth. But
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105582:9"/>I pray, miſtake me not, I ſpeake now what God is able to doe, I doe not ſay that God doth teach his people the whole knowledge of the whole truth; for in this life we know but in part; but I ſay, God is able to teach his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the whole knowledge of the whole truth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is the ableſt teacher of his people. Secondly, he is the ableſt for the manner, he cauſeth that he teacheth to take impreſſion upon the heart, which no other teacher is able to doe. Thirdly, he is the ableſt for meaſure, all the matter that is in all the faithfull Preachers in the world, they had it from him, as the fountaine and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of it, it is he that filled all the Prophets with matter, and all the Apoſtles, and all the faithfull Miniſters of the Word, looke what abilitie they have, they have it from him, looke what abilitie one hath above another, God gave it him, who diſtributeth to every one as he pleaſeth, all their knowledge, and abilities, and graces, are but ſtreames flowing from the fountaine; now looke what is in the chanell, there is much more in the fountaine, now God is the fountaine, they have but the ſtreames that run in the chanell, therefore God is the ableſt teacher for the meaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> As God is the ableſt teacher of his people, ſo he is the wiſeſt, and therefore the beſt inſtructor of his people: for the matter, it is wiſdome it ſelfe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7. for the manner, with infinite wiſdome, if we conſider Gods car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage towards the ſoule when he draws it to himſelfe; for the time, he comes in a ſeaſonable time to the ſoule, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to humble or comfort it; the Miniſter may apply comfort too ſoone unto a ſoule, or ſad them they ſhould comfort, and many times the Miniſter is poſed when he lights upon ſome kinde of people, knows not whether i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be beſt to apply comfort or terrour, or how to deale with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105582:9"/>the partie; but the wiſdome of God is ſuch as he knows what is ſutable to the ſoules condition, and what time is moſt ſeaſonable, he is wiſeſt for the time.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> God is the faithfulleſt teacher of his people, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beſt teacher; Miniſters may erre, or be unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to people, but God is a faithfull teacher and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor to his people; he is called <hi>the faithfull and true wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> Rev. 1.5. God is faithfull who hath called us unto the fellowſhip of his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt. Two wayes Miniſters may deale unfaithfully with their people; firſt, when they daube them with untempered morter, crying peace, peace, when they ſhould cry, bloud, and warre, and condemnation; as <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.11. <hi>They have healed the hurt of the daughter of my people with ſweet words, crying, peace, peace, when there is no peace:</hi> when Miniſters ſad the hearts of the righteous, and ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked, this is unfaithfull dealing with people; but ſecondly, Miniſters may deale unfaithfully with people, by teaching corrupt doctrine, when they are erroneous, when they teach lyes for truth, and diabolicall doctrine for the doctrine of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, when they turne people from the truth to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and lyes, and hereſies, ſtrong deluſions, as wofull experience ſhews in theſe dayes; it is the practice of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to ſeeke to turne people from the truth to fables; but God is a faithfull teacher of his people, he doth not flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any, but tell them right downe as it is with them; if he be not reconciled unto a ſoule in Jeſus Chriſt, he ſpeaks no peace to that ſoule, the poore ſoule may reade the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble through, but cannot finde God ſpeake one word of peace, God is faithfull in his teaching the ſoule; amongſt all the faithfulleſt Miniſters in the world, there is at ſome time or other more or leſſe a conniving at ſomething, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe they are great men, and they depend upon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105582:10"/>them, or intimate acquaintance, or neere friends, or fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-brethren, or ſome other reſpect; and if any man ſhould plead he is cleare in this particular, I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve him, for it is naturall to all, but God doth not nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more nor leſſe at any time deale unfaithfully with the ſoule, and therefore he is the faithfulleſt teacher.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> Becauſe God is the pitifulleſt teacher and inſtructor of his people, for though he denounce woes and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt the wicked, yet he is very tender and piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unto poore humble ſoules, that are dejected and caſt downe under the burden of ſinne, he pities the ſoule that he finds in its bloud, he is full of pitie and compaſſion, as the Pſalmiſt ſaith; and as he is the pitifulleſt, ſo he is the comfortableſt teacher to the ſoule; the matter he teaches is full of conſolation. Is a poore ſoule broken-hearted, ſee how comfortably he ſpeaks to ſuch a ſoule, as if he ſhould ſay, Tell that broken-hearted ſinner, I am neere to him, I will dwell with him, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.2. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 57.15. I have ſent Jeſus Chriſt to bind it up, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 61.1. Tell the poore ſoule, that is in depths of deſertion, and walkes in darkneſſe, and ſees no light, that he ſhould truſt in the Name of the Lord, and ſtay himſelfe upon his God; tell the poore ſoule, that pores upon its unworthineſſe, and worthleſneſſe, and want of grace, that there is an infinite worth in Jeſus Chriſt, an infinite worthineſſe in Jeſus Chriſt, a fulneſſe of grace in Chriſt, and therefore bid them be comforted; the Lord bids his Meſſengers ſpeak comfortably to his people, Comfort ye my people, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ye, will your God ſay, ſpeake comfortably to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> tell her that her iniquities are pardoned, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 40.1. The Lord gives his Miniſters a charge to comfort his people, tell them from mee, I would have them comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, tell them my thoughts are thoughts of peace and not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105582:10"/>of warre towards them; tell them it is the will of God that his people ſhould have ſtrong conſolation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17. tell them they ſhall not need to call my love into queſtion, for I have loved them with an everlaſting love, and with loving kindneſſe drawne them. With a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſuch like expreſſions in Scripture; and the Lord doth not onely propound this comfort to the ſoule, but cauſeth the ſoule to apply it; and this no other Miniſter can doe, therefore God is the pitifulleſt and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortableſt teacher of his people.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> God is the beſt inſtructor of his people, becauſe he is the powerfulleſt teacher of his people, he ſhews a divine authoritie in thoſe truths which he teacheth the ſoule. <hi>Job</hi> 36.22. <hi>God exalteth by his power; for who teacheth like him?</hi> We ſay of ſuch and ſuch a Miniſter, he is a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preacher, but yet the moſt powerfull preacher in the world cannot ſpeake ſo to a dead ſoule, as to make it live; but God teacheth with ſuch a power, that if he ſay to a dead ſoule live, it ſhall live, if he ſay to a hard heart be ſoft, it ſhall melt, and the proud ſpirit ſhall be humble, and the moſt ſtubborne rebellious ſinner ſhall ſtoope, which no other teacher can doe, therefore God is the ſoules beſt teacher, he is the moſt powerfull teacher.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>6</label> God is the beſt teacher and inſtructor of his people, becauſe he is the profitableſt teacher; he teacheth the ſoule nothing but that which is profitable; Miniſters may teach much matter that is unprofitable, though they be conſcientious, but all that God teacheth is profitable: and as all the matter is profitable, ſo he cauſeth all he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to profit by it; the Miniſter may teach a people a long time, and yet not make them profit by his Miniſtry; but God doth ſo teach the ſoule, as it ſhall profit by that which he teacheth, as <hi>Iſai.</hi> 48.17. God teacheth his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105582:11"/>to profit, and there is no leſſon God teacheth a ſoule, but it ſhall profit by it. I have done with the Reaſons, wee come in the next place to the Uſes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>1</label> To informe us, what a happy condition the Church of God is in, they are taught of God, and he is the beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructor of his people, it is one part of the Covenant of grace to teach his Church, and therefore the Church is in a happy condition: Firſt, becauſe it is a great honour and dignity to be taught of God; ſchollers think it an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be preferred to the higheſt ſchoole in the world, and to ſit on the higheſt forme; the ſchoole of Jeſus Chriſt exceeds all the ſchools in the world, and the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that is taught in this ſchoole, is ſuch tranſcendent matter, as from eternity to eternity is time little enough to admire; nothing in this ſchoole, but may cauſe admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the tutor, God, the matter, the wiſdome in God himſelfe, and the manner of teaching of it, by his Spirit. Secondly, the Church being taught of God, they ſhall be ſure to be taught the right way; he ſhall inſtruct and <hi>teach thee in the way thou ſhalt goe,</hi> Pſal. 32.8. He teacheth and inſtructeth his people in the right way; <hi>Thy eares ſhall heare a voyce behind thee, ſaying, This is the way,</hi> Iſai. 30.21. and therefore the condition of the Church muſt needs be happy, they ſhall be taught the right way.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> If God be the beſt teacher of his people, and it be ſuch a dignitie to be taught of God, how comes it to paſſe then that amongſt Gods people, or at leaſt ſuch as profeſſe themſelves to be Gods people, there is ſo much diviſions and diſſentions, and ſtrange opinions, and that they are ſo contrary one to another in judgement? when we conſider this, wee cannot conclude, that it is ſuch a dignitie to be taught of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> It is true, amongſt profeſſors at this day, there is much
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105582:11"/>difference in judgement; ſome are of one opinion, and ſome of another, ſome are falne into ſtrange and corrupt opinions, but this comes not to paſſe, becauſe God teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his people ſeverall wayes; but firſt, becauſe they doe not learne of God, for God is not the Author of the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors that abound amongſt profeſſors, but the Author of truth, and that he teacheth the ſoule is truth, and nothing but the truth, nothing but that which is agreeable to his will, and therefore it is not becauſe God teacheth them corrupt opinions, but becauſe they do not learne of God. Secondly, it comes to paſſe that amongſt profeſſors they hold ſtrange opinions, becauſe as God teacheth the truth and nothing but the truth to his people, ſo the Devill ſows the ſeeds of diviſion amongſt people, where God ſows wheate, the Devill ſowes tares; where God makes knowne his truth, there the Devill ſeeks to infect people with errors. Thirdly, it comes to paſſe by permittance, God is pleaſed to permit it, he permits it for two cauſes; firſt, for the good of his people, the Lord lets his owne people many times run into ſtrange opinions for a time, that he might bring them back againe, and eſtabliſh them the more firmly in the truth, and there are none to ſuch Chriſtians as theſe when the Lord hath brought them back againe, then they will acknowledge their weakneſſe, and how ſubject they are to be miſled. Ah, ſays the poore ſoule, I had like to have miſcarried, and been carried away with ſuch and ſuch corrupt opinions, had not the Lord in mercy brought me back againe; now they will walke more humbly, and now they will ſtand up for the truth, and defend it more boldly then they did formerly, they will adviſe their friends, and bid them take heed of being ſeduced; they will try the ſpirits for the time to come, whether they be of God or no, they will be more earneſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105582:12"/>with God for the time to come, to eſtabliſh them in the truth. And thus the Lord doth it for the good of his people. Secondly, the Lord permits it out of a juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to others, who though they be glorious profeſſors, yet becauſe their hearts are not ſound, he will diſcover them by this means, when they come to forſake the wayes and truths of Jeſus Chriſt, and run into this and that error, and then from one thing to another, till at the length they come to deny the Scriptures, and live pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanely. Thus many come to be diſcovered in theſe times. And ſecondly, he gives them up to their corrupt opinions, and this is a great judgement, when the Lord ſays to them as to <hi>Ephraim, He is joyned to Idols, let him alone,</hi> Hoſea 4.17. So when the Lord ſays to them, they are joyned to their corrupt opinions, let them alone, let them hold Atheiſme if they will, let them hold Arminia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, Arianiſme, Marcellianiſme, Nicolaitaniſme, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometiſme, Anabaptiſme, Antinomianiſme if they will, let them hold that the ſoule is mortall, and dyes with the body, and that the Word of God is written traditions, and when they have received the Spirit, the letter ſhould ceaſe, let them alone, I will give them over to theſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, becauſe they refuſe to be guided by the rule of truth, I will give them up to ſtrong deluſions, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>Becauſe they received not the truth that they might be ſaved, therefore God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions that they ſhould beleeve lyes, that they might be damned which beleeve not the truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe.</hi> But how is it poſſible you will ſay, that they ſhould fall from one corrupt opinion to another, do not their own conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces check them? I anſwer, the conſcience of an hereticke is a ſeared conſcience, their <hi>conſcience is ſeared with an hot iron,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.2. Who doth the Apoſtle meane there,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105582:12"/>you may ſee in the firſt verſe, ſuch as give heed unto ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of errours, and doctrines of devils, their conſciences are paſt feeling: When God hath once given a man or woman over, conſcience very ſeldome troubles them, though they fall into horrible blaſphemies, yet ſeldome or never their conſciences trouble them; why ſo? becauſe God hath given them over, and this makes the condition of a man or woman miſerable; the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.31. <hi>It is a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the living God;</hi> but it is a more fearfull thing to fall out of the hands of God, and therefore their condition is very fearfull.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>2</label> The ſecond Uſe is for reproofe; Seeing God is the beſt teacher and inſtructor of his people, it reproves them that reſt in mans teaching onely, thinke it enough if they come to the Word and Sacraments, and can cry, The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord, this is the Temple of the Lord, and their reſt, and thinke all is well with them, they ſhall moſt certainly goe to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but alas, poore ſoule, thou muſt know that the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Miniſtry of the Word will doe thee no good with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the inward operation of the Spirit, it is God that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auſeth his people to profit, and if thou be not taught of God, as well as of man, thy outward teaching will doe <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ee no good, thou thinkeſt it will carry thee to heaven, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it will make thy condemnation the greater, if thou be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot bettered by it. Our Saviour Chriſt did many great <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orkes amongſt them of <hi>Chorazin, Bethſaida,</hi> and <hi>Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>um,</hi> they might as well as thou bleſſe themſelves, they <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in a good condition; why ſo? becauſe they might ſay, Chriſt hath preached &amp; wrought many miracles amongſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and walked up and downe in our ſtreets, wee have had <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> company, ſurely we are a happy people; but ſee what
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105582:13"/>our Saviour Chriſt ſaith of them, <hi>they repented not:</hi> and what follows? <hi>Woe to thee Chorazin, woe to thee Bethſaida, and thou Capernaum that art lifted up to heaven, ſhalt be throwne downe to bell,</hi> Mat. 11.21, 22, 23. <hi>And it ſhall be more eaſie for them of the land of Sodome at the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then for you.</hi> So a people may be lifted up to heaven with meanes, and brought downe to hell for not profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by it, and their condemnation will be the greater; <hi>This is the condemnation, that light is come into the world, and men love darkneſſe,</hi> Joh. 3.19. This is the grand damning ſinne, this damnes people with a witneſſe, to live under the meanes of grace unprofitable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It likewiſe reproves them that take all their Religion upon truſt, never with the men of <hi>Berea,</hi> ſearch the Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. But if one come with one Doctrine and another with another, he knows not but that they may all ſpeake truth. And ſome againe tye their Religion to ſome particular mans ſleeve, all that ſuch a man or ſuch a man ſpeakes is truth, as if they were infallible, and contemne others in compariſon of them; what is this but to have mens perſons in admiration, as <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeakes? Now if God be the beſt inſtructor of his people, then we ſhould try the ſpirits whether they be of God; and though <hi>Paul,</hi> or an Angel from heaven ſhould come and preach contrary to Gods Word, let them be accurſed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>3</label> The third uſe is for terror; Is the Lord the beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructor of his people? then wofull is the condition of all them that deſpiſe the meanes of grace, that deſpiſe Gods teaching of the ſoule, either outwardly by the Miniſtry of the Word, or inwardly by the Spirit, that ſay unto God, <hi>Depart from us, for wee deſire not the knowledge of thy
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105582:13"/>wayes,</hi> Job 21.14. And when his Meſſengers call upon them to aske for the old way, which is the good way, and walke therein; they ſay, we will not walke therein; the condition of ſuch is very miſerable. See two places of Scripture for it, which might terrifie the heart of any wicked wretch, that deſpiſeth the meanes of grace; the one is in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.25. <hi>See that yee deſpiſe not him that ſpeaketh; for if they eſcaped not that refuſed him that ſpake on earth, much more ſhall we not eſcape if wee turne from him that ſpeaketh from heaven.</hi> Thoſe that ſlight Chriſt, and make a light account of him, refuſe him and his doctrine, there is no eſcaping for ſuch, how much more ſhall wee not eſcape? The Lord Jeſus Chriſt is the great Prophet of his Church, and <hi>all that will not heare this Prophet, ſhall be deſtroyed,</hi> Acts 3.23. Here is the miſery of ſuch poore ſoules, they ſhall be deſtroyed. And how might this ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie a poore ſoule, that contemnes the meanes of grace, if I turne from Chriſt, if I heare not Chriſt, I ſhall not eſcape, I ſhall be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It may ſerve to terrifie ſuch perſons as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in hearing lyes as well as truth, and delight in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt doctrine as well as the truth, that ſay to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Prophecy ſmooth things to us, and flatter us in our ſinnes. Conſider but one place of Scripture, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. laſt verſe, <hi>The Prophets prophecy lyes, and the Prieſts receive gifts, and my people delight therein, but what will yee then doe in the end thereof?</hi> As much as if he ſhould ſay, there will come an end, there will come a time when the Lord will call Miniſter and people to an account; but <hi>what will yee doe in the end thereof?</hi> It implyes the end will be a ſad end, ſuch an end as they ſhall not know what to doe when they come to give account unto God, how they have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and heard the Word.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:105582:14"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>4</label> Is for direction to all ſuch perſons as would not erre, goe to God and deſire him to teach thee, who is the beſt inſtructor of his people; many a poore ſoule is ready to ſay, there are ſo many ſeverall opinions abroad, that I am at a ſtand, I know not what is truth and what is errour, I know not what way to walke in, and, oh, that I could heare of that Miniſter that could direct me in the right way. My anſwer to ſuch is, goe to God and he can teach thee the right way, he <hi>leads his people by the paths of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe for his Names ſake,</hi> Pſal. 23. He knows thy condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and can proportion matter ſutable to thy conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But now the ſoule will object; But what ſhall I doe that I may be taught of God? For anſwer to this great Queſtion, wouldeſt thou be taught of God, obſerve theſe directions, and the Lord make them profitable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Wouldeſt thou have God teach thee? then attend the meanes of grace, the preaching of the Word: I told you God teacheth the ſoule outwardly by the Word as well as inwardly by the Spirit, and that man or woman may queſtion whether God teacheth them that doe neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the outward Miniſtry of the Word, they are counted <hi>bleſſed that waite at wiſdomes gates,</hi> Pro. 8.33. And ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Deſpiſe not prophecying, try all things, and keepe that which is good,</hi> ſo that that ſoule that would be taught of God, muſt attend the means, the preaching of the word is the outward meanes God hath appointed to convert a ſoule, and as to convert, ſo to build up the ſoule by; for by the ſame meanes that he converts, he builds up, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it's a ſtrange opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that when a man is converted by the Miniſtry of the Word and Spirit, that he ſhould ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and run into a corner to build up himſelfe; he that would be taught of God, muſt attend the outward means by which the Lord teacheth the ſoule.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:105582:14"/>
            <p> Secondly, Wouldeſt thou have God teach thee? then be much in prayer, ſeeke unto God to teach thee; <hi>David</hi> knew much of God, was able to teach his teachers, and yet he is earneſt with God to teach him; <hi>ſhew me, thy way, O Lord,</hi> Pſal. 25.4. <hi>Lord teach me to doe thy will,</hi> Pſal. 143.11. <hi>And thou art my God, let thy good Spirit lead me into the land of uprightneſſe;</hi> As much as if the Prophet ſhould have ſayd, Lord, I have a perverſe ſpirit, thy Spirit is good, let thy good Spirit lead me, ſo goe to God, and challenge his promiſe, and ſay, Lord, thou haſt promiſed that the eares of thy People ſhall heare a voyce behinde them, ſaying, This is the way, walke in it, and yee ſhall find reſt. Lord, I am an ignorant wretch, ſubject to erre and miſcarry, Lord accompliſh thy promiſe, ſhew mee the way thou wouldeſt have me walke in, Lord ſuffer me not to miſcarry. And this is the ſecond meanes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Acknowledge thy ignorance, if thou wouldeſt have God to teach thee; there are many take up opinions with a reſolution to hold them, be they right or wrong, and are as confident it is truth they hold, as if they were infallible in this life, in ſo much as no argument will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them, they know enough, and ſcorne to be better inſtructed then they are. Now it is not ſuch God will teach; but as our Saviour Chriſt ſays, <hi>The whole need not the Phyſitian, but thoſe that are ſicke;</hi> ſo God ſays to theſe, you know enough already, you ſhall not need that I teach you; the knowing need not to be taught, but thoſe that are ignorant, that is, thoſe that ſee their ignorance, and acknowledge it. The way to have God teach us, is to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our ignorance; <hi>David</hi> in praying to God to teach him, acknowledges his ignorance, and his need of Gods teaching; the way to become wiſe, is to become a ſoole, to acknowledge our ignorance and folly; for <hi>he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105582:15"/>that thinkes he knoweth any thing, knoweth nothing as he ought to know,</hi> 1 Cor. 8.2.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Wouldeſt thou have God teach thee? then eye him in all thy wayes; <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.6. <hi>In all thy wayes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him, and he ſhall direct thy paths.</hi> Surely that ſoule that thinks moſt upon God, and eyes him at all times, places, and companies, and ſeeks direction from God about every imployment, it is that ſoule that God will teach.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, Wouldeſt thou be taught of God? then be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and feare to offend him; <hi>Who ſo among you feares the Lord, him will he teach,</hi> Pſal. 25.12. <hi>And he will teach the humble his way,</hi> verſ. 9. That ſoule that truly feares him, with a filiall feare, and lyes humble and low before the Lord, the Lord will teach; but it is not ſo with the proud, <hi>he beholds them afar off, he reſiſts them;</hi> ſhew a man that hath a proud ſpirit, he will ſtand upon it, and he knows more then all the Miniſters can tell him, and it is not for any to direct him, but he thinkes that he is better able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them, he is ready to condemne all that joyn not with him in opinion; and do but obſerve him, and ſee if he run not from one thing to another, from one corrupt opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto another, untill at length he be fallen quite from true Chriſtianitie; Why ſo? he is proud, and God doth not teach him, or if he belong to God, you ſhall ſee God will lay him as low on the other ſide, before ever he will comfort him; but the humble ſoule that lyes low at the throne of grace, crying, Lord, I am a vile wretched igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant creature; thou art heaven, but I am hell, it is theſe God will teach; then wouldeſt thou have God teach thee? be humble.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, Wouldeſt thou have God teach thee? then live in the practice of that which he hath already taught thee,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105582:15"/>and this is the way to know more, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.17. <hi>If any man doe my will, be ſhall know my doctrine.</hi> The way to know more, is to practice what wee know already. And theſe are the meanes thou ſhouldeſt uſe if thou wouldeſt have God teach thee.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But I have ſought God in the uſe of the meanes, and God gives me no anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> If thou haſt been inticed to ſome corrupt opinion, and thou thinkeſt it may be it is truth, and thou haſt ſought God concerning it, and God hath given thee no preſent reſolution, thou muſt know God doth by this prove thee, to ſee whether thou wilt ſtand conſtant and ſtedfaſt in the truth: ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1. <hi>If there ariſe a Prophet, ſaying, Let us goe after other Gods, hearken not to him, for the Lord your God proveth you.</hi> Is there any ariſe amongſt you that ſay, let us goe after new truths, new light? the Lord proveth you by them, to ſee whether you will forſake him or no, and therefore he gives no preſent anſwer; but know thus much, that if thou conſtantly ſeeke him in the uſe of the meanes, though he give not a preſent anſwer, yet in his due time he will give an anſwer, and cleare up the truth to thee.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> You call them heretiques and broachers of new truths and new light, which you call errours, but I cannot ſee but they are holy men, and live ſanctified lives, and can alledge more texts of Scripture for that they hold, then you can alledge againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The greater is the triall that God tryes thee with, but this can be no ſufficient ground for thee to follow them preſently, becauſe they ſeeme to live holy lives; for if they ſhould live prophane, then none that are conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious would regard them. An hypocrite will live a holy life outwardly, yea ſhame many a child of God, yet I am
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105582:16"/>not to be of the judgement of an hypocrite, becauſe he lives a holy life; the devill will allow an heretique to live a holy life, becauſe it is advantageous to his Kingdome, and Satan for his own ends transformes himſelfe into an Angel of light, and therefore no marvaile if his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters doe ſo: it is ſaid of heretiques, <hi>They are deceitfull workers, transforming themſelves into Angels of light,</hi> yea, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Apoſtles of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.13. And in the 15. verſe, they <hi>transforme themſelves as though they were the Miniſters of righteouſneſſe.</hi> So likewiſe it is ſaid of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, <hi>They come in ſheeps-cloathing, but inwardly are rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Wolves;</hi> and therefore ſaith Chriſt, <hi>beware of them,</hi> Mat. 7.15. And wheras thou ſay'ſt that they bring Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for that they ſpeake. I anſwer, ſo doe the Papiſts to prove, that the bread and wine in the Sacrament is the very body and bloud of Chriſt, how many Scriptures doe they alledge in the foure <hi>Evangeliſts?</hi> And the <hi>Arminians</hi> alledge many Scriptures for to prove a childe of God may fall totally and finally from grace; and yet both ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry corrupt opinions; <hi>Try the ſpirits, whether they be of God or no,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; now the Apoſtle ſhould not need to bid us try the ſpirits, were there not a lying ſpirit that imitates the true Spirit; for if the lying ſpirit did ſeduce in a way contrary to the true Spirit, there would never be ſo much miſchiefe done, but the lying ſpirit imitates the true Spirit. It is ſaid of ſeducers, <hi>They come in the Name of Chriſt, and deceive many,</hi> Mat. 24.5. they could never doe ſo much miſchieſe, did they not come in the Name of Chriſt. Wicked people want not holy preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to cover their wicked actions. Thoſe in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66. that caſt out the people of God ſay, <hi>Let the Lord be glorified;</hi> and they that kill the people of God think they do God good ſervice, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.2. They would cover theſe wicked
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105582:16"/>actions with a cloake of Religion, ſaying, <hi>Let the Lord be glorified:</hi> This is the way, Beloved, to make the Scriptures moſe of wax, to grant every heretique their interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Scripture, ſo that their alledging Scripture can be no ſufficient ground for thee to yeeld to their corrupt opinions, but they coming under this notion, the greater is thy triall, and God doth prove thee, to ſee whether thou wilt defend the truth or no.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But thou wilt ſay, it may be, how cometh it to paſſe, that many that have ſought God, and been earneſt in the uſe of the means, have miſcarried and fallen into corrupt and ſtrange opinions, as you call them, then, if God tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth thoſe that uſe the means?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Firſt, Becauſe the fault may be in their ſeeking, they may ſeeke God with an Idol in their hearts, and God may anſwer them according to the Idol in their hearts, that is, they may make choice of ſome corrupt opinion, and upon the matter are reſolved to hold it, are unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling any body ſhould confute it, cannot indure the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that preacheth againſt it, and with might and maine defends it, are vexed that any Scripture ſhould ſeeme to croſſe it, and yet they will ſeek unto God for his appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation in it; juſt as <hi>Balaam</hi> did, you know he was hired to curſe the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Numb.</hi> 22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23. chap. and he was very willing withall, he lik't the motion well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, but he would have God approve of it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he builds Altars, and offers Sacrifice, and would faine have Gods approbation in it. Now when we ſeeke thus, God may anſwer according to the Idol in the heart; and this you may ſee in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Every man that ſetteth up his Idols in his heart, and comes to a Prophet to inquire of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I will anſwer him according to the Idols in his heart.</hi> When a man ſetteth up Idols in his heart, this corrupt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105582:17"/>opinion, and that corrupt opinion, and then come to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of God, God may out of a juſt judgement anſwer them according to the Idols in their hearts. And this may be one Reaſon why though people ſeeke God and uſe the meanes, yet they may miſcarry, the fault is in their ſeeking.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It may come to paſſe amongſt ſuch as are godly, that they may ſeeke God, and uſe the meanes, and yet miſcarry for a time, that they might be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſtabliſhed in the truth, when the Lord brings them backe againe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Some though they ſeeke God and uſe the meanes, yet they may miſcarry, becauſe they have not true grace, ſuch as may be compared to the <hi>Stony ground,</hi> they want roote, and theſe, though they doe ſeeke God, yet they may miſcarry; for being hypocriticall profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, God will not regard their prayer; as <hi>Job</hi> 27.8, 9. <hi>What hope hath the hypocrite when God takes away his ſouls? Will he heare his cry?</hi> God will not regard their prayer; and ſecondly, being but hypocrites, they are not under a promiſe of perſeverance in the truth, the godly are under a promiſe of perſeverance in the truth, and therefore though they ſhould miſcarry for a time, yet the Lord will bring them backe againe; but another that hath no true grace, when he miſcarries, it may be, for any thing we know, a finall miſcarriage, he though he make a glorious profeſſion, yet is not under the promiſe, the other is; every graft the Father plants into Chriſt, he prunes and dreſſes, and makes fruitfull, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.2. Yea he ſends his Spirit, and that leads them into all truth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26. Now this may be another ground, why people may ſeeke God, and uſe the meanes, and yet miſcarry, becauſe the perſons that ſeeke are not truly godly.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:105582:17"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But may, ſome ſay, if the cauſe ſtand thus, how ſhall I know whether I be taught of God, yea or no?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Firſt, If God teach thee, then thou art very carefull in the uſe of the meanes, thou art carefull to obſerve all the direction I have given, to attend the outward meanes of grace, and thou art much in prayer, thou doeſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thine ignorance, and ſo of all the reſt. Now exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine whether thou be very carefull in the uſe of theſe meanes, or no, if thou be, then ſurely God teacheth thee.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If thou be taught of God, thou art in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with him, it is one part of the Covenant of grace, <hi>they ſhall be all taught and drawne of God,</hi> therefore examine whether thou be in Covenant with God, yea or no, if thou be not in Covenant with God, thou art not under the promiſe of Gods teaching of thee.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If thou be taught of God, then he teacheth thee to know thy ſelfe aright, he ſhews thee thy ſelfe in the glaſſe of his Word, and to know him aright, and then the more thou knoweſt, the more humble thou art; Doeſt thou lie humbly under gifts, and parts, and knowledge, and ſay, All is free mercy, and we have nothing but what we have received from God? Thus it is with that ſoule that God teacheth. <hi>Job</hi> 42.2. <hi>When he looked upon God, then he abhorred himſelfe in duſt and aſhes;</hi> and <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.19. <hi>After I was inſtructed, I ſmote upon my thigh, I was aſhamed and confounded.</hi> Thus it is with the ſoule, when God tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth it, the more God teacheth it, the more humble it <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; art thou puft up with thy knowledge, doth it make <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ee eſteeme of thy ſelfe above others? then thou mayeſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſtion, if thou haſt knowledge, whether thou haſt any <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing elſe; for if thou hadſt grace, thou wouldeſt be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and low in thine owne eyes.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105582:18"/>
            <p> Fourthly, If God teacheth thee, then thou doeſt live a pious godly life; <hi>for the grace of God which bringeth ſalve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, teacheth us to deny ungodlineſſe, and worldly luſts, and to live holily, righteouſly, and ſoberly in this preſent World,</hi> Tit. 2.11, 12. Thoſe that out of pretence of new light, live looſly, ſay the Scriptures are written traditions, and they pray not in the family, they crave not a bleſſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their meate; aske them, why ſo, they anſwer, they know their liberty by Chriſt, and they contemne the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God, cenſure all that are not of the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to be in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and Idolaters; it is evident they are not taught of God; for thoſe that God teacheth, he teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them <hi>to deny ungodlineſs, and worldly luſts, and to live ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily, righteouſly, and ſoberly in this preſent world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, If God teach thee, thou art a growing and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering Chriſtian, thou doeſt grow in grace; for he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his Schollers to profit by his inſtructions; it is not with thoſe that God teacheth, as it is with thoſe that get no good by going to Schoole ſeven yeares, but thoſe God teacheth, he teacheth to profit; <hi>Unto you that feare my Name, ſhall the Sun of righteouſneſſe ariſe with healing under his wings, and they ſhall goe forth and grow as the calves of the ſtall;</hi> Thoſe that God teacheth, they are a people grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in grace, and knowledge, and as they ſhall grow, ſo they ſhall perſevere. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 40. verſ. the laſt, <hi>They ſhall run and not be weary, they ſhall walke and not faint:</hi> it ſhall not be ſaid of them, <hi>They are young Saints, and old Devils,</hi> but they ſhall <hi>bring forth fruit in old age,</hi> Pſal. 92.13. And they ſhall be ſelfe-denying Chriſtians, that is one inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that Jeſus Chriſt, the great Prophet of his Church, teacheth his people, <hi>Mar.</hi> 8.34. Now examine thy ſelfe, art thou taught of God? then thou art a growing Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an? Art thou a growing ſelfe-denying perſevering Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian?
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105582:18"/>then it is a ſigne that God teacheth thee, and thou art a perſevering Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, If God teach thee, thou doeſt ſeeke him in the uſe of thoſe meanes which thou haſt found him in; haſt thou found him in the preaching of the Word? the day of his power hath come upon thee: and haſt thou found him in prayer? thou wilt ſeeke him in the uſe of theſe meanes ſtill; the way is not to ſeparate from the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances thou haſt found God in, and to neglect holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for then thou mayeſt want of Gods teaching of thee, and thou wilt not thrive then in grace, but thou muſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend thoſe meanes thou haſt found God in, and not ſuch means as thou knoweſt not whether thou ſhalt find God in, or no.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>5</label> Exhortation. Is God the beſt teacher of his people? goe to God, and beſeech him to teach thee.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Conſider the neceſſitie of Gods teaching thee, as our Saviour Chriſt ſaith to <hi>Peter, If I waſh thee not, thou haſt no part in me;</hi> ſo, if God teach thee not, thou haſt no intereſt in him, for all his people are taught and drawne of him; there is a neceſſitie of Gods teaching of thee, in reſpect of thy need, thou art a nothing-creature, an ignorant creature, ſubject to erre, and to be miſled, thou doeſt ſtand in need of Gods teaching.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider God is the beſt inſtructor, let this move thee to goe to him, he is able to reſolve thy doubts, he can cleare up truths to thee, he can propound matter ſutable to thy condition; and as he is able to teach thee, ſo it is his promiſe to teach thoſe he enters into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. ſeek him in the promiſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let the leſſons God teacheth his people move thee to goe to him, and beſeech him to teach thee, they are ſoule-raviſhing leſſous being once learned, they bring
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105582:19"/>in ſoule-raviſhing comfort unto the ſoule, the matter in them is ſoule-raviſhing matter; tranſcendent matter, ſcholars that affect their ſtudies, many times they are taken up with the eloquence of the matter, the leſſons that God teacheth the ſoule, are ſuch tranſcendent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſuch great myſteries, as from eternitie to eternitie, is time little enough for men and Angels to admire at, for the very Angels admire it, and deſire to pry into it; then let the excellency of the matter move thee to go to God, and beſeech him to teach thee.</p>
            <p>One motive more; Conſider if God teach thee, and thou learne of him, then he will teach thee the <hi>way, truth,</hi> and <hi>life,</hi> which is Chriſt Jeſus, and then to be ſure thou ſhalt not miſcarry. Oh, Brethren, be exhorted to goe to God, and beſeech him to teach you; and as at all times, ſo eſpecially now in theſe diſtracted times, when there is abundance of counterfeit coine abroad, every one will view his money well when he takes it, for feare he ſhould be cheated. Oh, Beloved, there is but one way, one truth, and life, and therefore abundance of counterfeit Religion abroad; how many plead for a toleration of all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that every man might uſe his conſcience? how many proclaime open warre againſt the Scriptures? how many vent out blaſphemies againſt the perſons in the Trinitie? how many cry downe the Morall Law for a rule, though it be one part of the Covenant of grace? <hi>I will write my Lawes in your hearts, and cauſe you to walke in my wayes;</hi> how many run up and downe the Country, ſeducing and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſciples after them, ſome into one corrupt opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſome into another; and it ſtands every one that deſires to know the truth in hand, to looke what coine they take, then doe it not I pray, ſeeing Gods Word doth know of but one way, truth, and life, that is ſafe, there is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105582:19"/>but one true Religion, and therefore many are ſeduced in theſe times; and the devill never had ſuch a ſtring to harp upon, as he hath now, new light, and new truth, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> many thouſands will daſh their braines out upon this rocke, if the Lord be not mercifull unto them; and this will terrifie them when death comes, and the day of Judgement, when many will cry out, Oh, I did thinke ſuch a one, and ſuch an one, would not have miſled me, I tooke them to be holy men, ſuch as knew much of God, ſuch as were more eminent then others, but now I ſee they are miſtaken, and I am miſtaken, I am an undone man, and I am an undone woman, I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken God, and his truth, and now God will forſake mee for ever. Lay theſe things to heart, Brethren, I tell you, the Church never had ſuch a triall as now it hath, now are the times come that was ſpoken of, <hi>in the laſt dayes ſhall come perilous times,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.1. in which men will not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure <hi>ſound doctrine, but are turned from the truth to fables,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4. They come in the Name of Chriſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive many, and the Lord onely knows who may be ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by them, the Lord knows but it may be my husband may be ſeduced, may the wife ſay; or the Lord knows but it may be my wife may be ſeduced, may the husband ſay; the Lord knows, may parents ſay, but it may be our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren may be ſeduced and drawne from the wayes and truths of Chriſt, into dangerous &amp; damnable errors, and what ſhall become of our children then? Conſider theſe things, and let them move you to goe to God, and beſeech him to teach you and direct you; and you that are huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, carry your wives to God, and beſeech him to teach them, and to keepe them from miſcarrying; and you that are wives, carry your husbands to God, and intreat him
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105582:20"/>to teach your husbands; and you parents, carry your children and ſervants to God, and ſay, Oh, Lord, we live in ſad times, miſcarrying times, little did we thinke ever to have lived in ſuch times, Lord keepe us cloſe to thy ſelfe, and eſtabliſh us in the truth; Lord keepe my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, keepe my wife, keepe our children and ſervants, and carry your neighbours to God, and beſeech him to looke upon them, and ſtabliſh them in the truth. And this is a notable means to keep us from miſcarrying.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, when God hath anſwered your prayers, and ſetled you in the truth, thy ſelfe, or thy husband, or wife, or children, or neighbours, then give him the praiſe and glory of it: O Lord, ſuch a one had like to have miſcarried, but thou haſt ſetled him in the truth, bleſſed be thy Name for it. The Lord make theſe things profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and effectuall by the inward operation of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, who is the beſt teacher of his people.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
